<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Learn Piano the Hard Way</title><link>https://learnpianothehardway.com/</link><description>Recent content on Learn Piano the Hard Way</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-uk</language><atom:link href="https://learnpianothehardway.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Buy this book</title><link>https://learnpianothehardway.com/buy-book/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learnpianothehardway.com/buy-book/</guid><description>&lt;p>I believe education should be freely available. I also believe that authors,
educators, and teachers should be compensated for their work.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is the responsibility of us who can afford it to finance free and public
education. If you have the means to &amp;ldquo;buy&amp;rdquo; this book and you have gained value
from it, I would ask that you pay for the book.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are two price points below. A basic price point at $10 NZD, and a generous
one for $20 NZD. If you wish to donate more, you can purchase the book multiple
times. You will &lt;em>not&lt;/em> get a PDF for the book, you will &lt;em>not&lt;/em> get any special
perks. While I would like to keep this book up on the internet forever, the
truth is that we don&amp;rsquo;t know what the future holds. Because this book is on the
internet, it&amp;rsquo;s not really anywhere. If you are worried about the website not
being available any more, you can download the source code for the book
completely for free at &lt;a href="https://github.com/hugomiddeldorp/learn-piano-the-hard-way">this
URL&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Introduction</title><link>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-1/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="what-is-a-great-pianist">What is a great pianist?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Is it someone who is technically precise, who can play fast with no mistakes? Is it someone who has a deep emotional connection to the music and is able to communicate it? Is greatness synonymous with uniqueness &amp;ndash; does this pianist need to bring a unique interpretation to the music?
Everyone will have different answers, or at least everyone will weigh certain qualities differently.
There is no right answer, nonetheless, answering this question for ourselves is crucial to achieving our goal of becoming a great pianist.
&lt;div id="sidenote" class="lg:absolute lg:right-0 lg:w-80 lg:-mt-10 lg:-mr-88 leading-tight text-base mb-4 px-2 border-y-2 border-customblue-400/75 py-4 text-customblue-400/75">
 Throughout this book, I will give exercises and activities to help you engage with the reading material more. Reading by itself is not sufficient for understanding, &lt;em>doing&lt;/em> is crucial. I highly recommend doing these exercises to test and solidify your understanding.
&lt;/div> 

By answering this question, we can identify the discrete skills required, and we can reason our way to acquiring them.
While defining exactly what a great pianist is might be difficult, pointing one out is not. In fact, you might already have a few names in mind.
These pianists, these idols, can embody what you hope to achieve before you can put words to it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Musicality</title><link>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-2/</guid><description>&lt;p>The idea of musicality is surrounded with a shroud of mysticism. It is often thought that people are either born musical or they are not, and that musicality isn&amp;rsquo;t really a skill that can be learned.
Taken at face value, that proposition is obviously wrong: babies are born with very little knowledge and acquire almost all of it through learning.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A stronger argument can be made that there is a critical period in children&amp;rsquo;s development after which musicality cannot be learned. This is a harder claim to refute. If we look at most of the great pianists of history, almost all of them were child prodigies. The evidence seems to be clear.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Be a Great Teacher</title><link>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-3/</guid><description>&lt;p>As you embark on the journey to master piano playing and become a great musician, you will need to wear two hats: the student, and the teacher.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As artists, we are often severe and self critical. There is always something wrong with our work and we put ourselves down for it. We are never good enough.
Clearly separating between student and teacher mode avoids the self-hatred trap:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>We can adopt a problem solving mentality (teacher) rather than beating ourselves up for being bad (student).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We can separate playing and expression (student) with review and critique (teacher).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We can treat ourselves with more compassion. (Your students wouldn&amp;rsquo;t last very long with you if you treated them the same way you treat yourself&amp;hellip;)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Self teaching takes a lot of focus and discipline. It&amp;rsquo;s often difficult to get the perspective we need to progress. Having these two modes forces us to switch perspectives, which will often be healthy and productive.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Repertoire</title><link>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-4/</guid><description>&lt;p>While learning music can be done away from an instrument, at some point if we
want to learn piano, we have to spend time at the instrument. Learning
repertoire is the only way to learn how to play the piano. You will not learn
how to play by learning scales, arpeggios, or any other exercises. Those can be
useful additions, but they are not a replacement for learning pieces composed by
real people. Everything we learn should be in the context of music.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How to Learn</title><link>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-5/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="before-starting">Before starting&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>By now you have hopefully chosen a piece that seems to be at the correct level,
and you have probably listened to at least one recording of it. Before starting
to learn the notes of the piece, I would recommend putting in a little bit of
extra time to learn about the piece and the composer first.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Find 2-3 recordings of the piece. Avoid digital piano recordings as they will
not have the same depth of playing as physical pianos. You can look up the name
of the piece on Youtube or Spotify and try to find recordings by great pianists.
Refer back to &lt;a href="https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-2/#listening">Musicality&lt;/a> for how to listen.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Integrative Approach</title><link>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-6/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-6/</guid><description>&lt;p>At the core of my teaching philosophy sits the Integrative Approach: a way to
understand and practise music from the top-down.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Traditionally, music might be taught by first learning a scale, then applying it
to a piece. You might learn what a D minor triad is, and then use it in a piece.
You might learn about the VI - V - I progression, and then apply it in music. I
propose a different approach, where we start with the music, start with the
sounds, the emotion, the meaning, and then dig deeper and notice that it is made
up of a major scale, or a D minor triad. Learning music that way, we understand
the whole before the parts. We don&amp;rsquo;t need to learn how they integrate, that&amp;rsquo;s
just how they are. We learn how to break them down.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sight-reading</title><link>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-7/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-7/</guid><description>&lt;p>A few hundred years ago among the musically educated, picking up sheet music for
the first time and playing it was akin to picking up a book and reading it out
loud. During those times, in order to even be called a musician, you had to be
able to sight-read. Most of the music that was played was never rehearsed, and
only played few times. Music was not written to be remembered, it was written to
be communicated to other musicians. Steadily, as memorisation became more common
and having a &lt;em>repertoire&lt;/em> was expected of musicians, the need for sight-reading
decreased. Nowadays few people would make the comparison between sight-reading
music and reading a book out loud.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Practising</title><link>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-8/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-8/</guid><description>&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s begin with the end and work our way back: we want to become a great
pianist, we have identified the requisite qualities (namely musicality and
technicality), and we have seen how to acquire them (through the integrative
approach of learning repertoire). We have the destination, we know the direction,
now we need to make the path. We need to practise.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before I discuss how I structure my practise, I want to deal with the two most
common roadblocks people experience regarding practising.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Creativity</title><link>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-9/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-9/</guid><description>&lt;p>All musicality requires creativity. Whether you are interpreting a piece of
music written by another composer, arranging it for a different ensemble,
composing your own music, or improvising over the music of someone else, you are
involved in a creative process. Even something as trivial as creating as
exercise out of a section of music is a creative act. If you are not interested
in further pursuing creativity in music in the form of composition and
improvisation, this section may not be necessary. I would suggest, however, to
give composition and improvisation a go for two reasons: it is fun, and it is
also a great way to understand music.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ear training</title><link>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-10/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-10/</guid><description>&lt;p>Have you ever been impressed with someone&amp;rsquo;s ability to hear a song once and
instantly be able to play it? A proportion of musicians who have that ability
have what we call perfect pitch: the ability to instantly recognise the name of
a note based on its pitch. This ability is developed early in childhood and
cannot be developed later. The rest of the musicians who can play music by ear
have relative pitch. They may not be able to tell you the name of a note based
on its pitch, but give them a point of reference, and they will be able to tell
you anything. Relative pitch, unlike perfect pitch, can be trained, and can also
be more powerful than perfect pitch.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Performing</title><link>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-11/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-11/</guid><description>&lt;p>You could be a great pianist and choose never to perform, but I think that would
be a shame. There is nothing quite like the rush, pleasure, and feeling of
accomplishment that comes from delivering a great performance. You spend all
this time working in private, building your skills, and you only keep it for
yourself, pity! As an audience member, there is nothing I love more than seeing
someone I care about strive and succeed in an artistic endeavour. You build a
closeness with people that can&amp;rsquo;t be achieved any other way. Performing may not
be for everyone but I think you would be doing yourself a disservice if you
never gave it a fair go.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Reference Materials</title><link>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-12/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://learnpianothehardway.com/book/chapter-12/</guid><description>&lt;p>This page is unfinished. I have high expectations for the reference material and
unfortunately, I don&amp;rsquo;t have enough time at the moment to make something that
will meet that standard. For now, I have collected the resources on which this
section will eventually be based.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="technique">Technique&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="seymour-fink-mastering-piano-technique-a-guide-for-students-teachers-and-performers">Seymour Fink, Mastering Piano Technique: A Guide for Students, Teachers and Performers&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This book is the most complete and comprehensive look at piano technique that I
have encountered so far. Fink breaks down piano technique into primary
movements, which when combined encompass the entirety of the physical components
of piano playing. It completely revolutionised my technique and the way that I
approach teaching it.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>